Guide to the John T. Gilroy Papers AIA.011
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
John T. Gilroy Papers
Bulk, 1990-1999
1919-2002
AIA.011
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
4.0 linear feet in 2 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, 1 oversize flat box, and 1 small artifacts box
John T. Gilroy was a member and officer of the County Fermanagh Social and Benevolent Association of New York, and of Ancient Order of Hibernians Division 3 (William B. Burke), New York County. This collection consists of personal material, as well as materials concerning Gilroy's membership in various social and fraternal organizations, including the Ancient Order of Hibernians, New York County, Division 3 and the County Fermanagh Social & Benevolent Association of New York. Materials include artifacts, photographs, correspondence, meeting minutes, event programs, newspaper clippings, and various organizational records.
Gilroy, John T.
Historical/Biographical Note
John T. Gilroy was a member and officer of the County Fermanagh Social and Benevolent Association of New York, and of Ancient Order of Hibernians Division 3 (William B. Burke), New York County.
Scope and Contents note
This collection consists of materials documenting John Giroy's membership and participation in various Irish American organizations in the greater New York City area, as well as other materials from his personal life. Materials include artifacts, photographs, correspondence, videocassettes, meeting minutes, event programs, newspaper clippings, and various organizational records from the Ancient Order of Hibernians (New York County, Division 3) and the County Fermanagh Social & Benevolent Association of New York. Personal mateials document Gilroy's education and his engagement with the Irish American community of New York.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Researchers interested in using audiovisual materials in this collection (films, cassette tapes, VHS tapes, et cetera) must use a digitized copy, which we refer to as an access copy. Researchers may view an item’s original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that already have already been digitized are noted in the collection’s finding aid and can be requested in our reading room; materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. These requests are free of charge and can be made in anticipation of your visit. The process typically takes four to six weeks. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@library.nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A librarian will respond to you with further information.
Related Archival Materials
Archives of Irish America County Societies Collection (AIA 003)
Archives of Irish America Collection on the Ancient Order of Hibernians (AIA 046)
John T. Ridge Collection (AIA 068)
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Collection donated by Joan Richardson, acting as executor for the estate of John T. Gilroy, in 2004. The accession number associated with this collection is 1997.010.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into three series, as follows:
I. Ancient Order of Hibernians, New York County, Division 3 (William B. Burke)
II. County Fermanagh Social & Benevolent Association of New York
III. Personal Materials
Ancient Order of Hibernians.; Irish Americans |x Societies, etc.; Irish Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Political activities.; Irish Americans |z New York (State) |z New York.
- I. Ancient Order of Hibernians, New York County, Division 3 (William B. Burke)
  - General, 1985-1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1985-1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Financial, 1985-1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Legal, 1985-1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Membership, 1985-1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Membership Applications and Transfer Cards, 1985-1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1985-1998 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ephemera, 1985-1998 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - New York County Board Minutes, 1985-1998 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - New York County St. Patrick's Day Parade and Celebration Committee, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - New York State Board Correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - New York State By-Laws, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - New York State: Empire State Hibernian Newsletter, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - National Board: Constitution, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - National Board: Correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - National Board: Forms, circa 1985-1998 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - National Board: Freedom for All Ireland, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - National Board: Membership Brochure, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - National Board: Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1992-2002 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Ladies Auxiliary: Correspondence, 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- II. County Fermanagh Social and Benevolent Association of New York
  - General, 1987-1997 (Box 1, Folder 21-25)
  - Fermanagh Gaelic Football Club Dance Videos, Mar 8, 1997; 2.0 videocassettes (Box 2)
  - Plaque, undated (Box 4)
  - Photographs, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- III. Personal Materials
  - Altar Boy Handbook, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Artifacts: Banner, Plaque, Plate, undated (Box 4)
  - Artifacts: Coins, Copper Baby Shoes, Hugh Gilroy's Medal from Irish War of Independence, Pipe, undated (Box 5)
  - Baby Book, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Cardinal Hayes High School, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
  - City Hall, New York Video, Jul 12, 1996; 1.0 videocassette (Box 2)
  - Communion and Confirmation, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Consulate General, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Curious Journey: The Fight for Irish Freedom, 1978; 1.0 videocassette (Box 2)
  - Fort Hamilton Video, Jul 13, 1996; 1.0 videocassette (Box 2)
  - Frontline: "Death of a Terrorist", 1989; 1.0 videocassette (Box 3)
  - Gaelic Park (Bronx, NY) Video, Jul 20, 1996; 1.0 videocassette (Box 2)
  - Hang Up Your Brightest Colors: The Life and Death of Michael Collins, 1997; 1.0 videocassette (Box 2)
  - "Heritage" Video, Jul 15, 1996; 1.0 videocassette (Box 2)
  - "Investigation into a Terrorist Bombing" Video, undated; 2.0 videocassettes (Box 3, Box 2)
  - Irish American Center (Mineola) Videos, Jul 19, 1996; 2.0 videocassettes (Box 2)
  - Irish American Organizations, 1988-2000 (Box 1, Folder 33-36, Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Irish Directory, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Irish Republicanism, 1980-1991 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Joe Doherty Rally Video, 1990; 1.0 videocassette (Box 3)
  - Lough Derg: An Island Sanctuary, Oct 1985; 1.0 videocassette (Box 3)
  - Musical Recordings, undated; 4.0 reels (Box 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Off Our Knees: 1968-1988 Civil Rights to National Rights, 1.0 videocassette (Box 3)
  - Parade Video, 1999; 1.0 videocassette (Box 2)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - The Rights of Man: The Concert for Joseph Doherty, 1991 (Box 3)
  - St. Brendan's Church (Bronx, NY), 1983 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - St. Luke's School (Bronx, NY), 1947, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 9-11)
  - St. Patrick's Video, Jul 12, 1996; 2.0 videocassettes (Box 2)
  - St. Patrick's Day (New York and Dublin) Video, 1991; 1.0 videocassette (Box 3)
  - St. Patrick's Day Parade, 1985-2001 (Box 2, Folder 11)